Guide to New Neighbors: Sunset Park's Chinese Community oral histories 1994.007
Brooklyn Historical Society
New Neighbors: Sunset Park's Chinese Community records
Bulk, 1993-1994
1992-1996
1994.007
Brooklyn Historical Society
6.42 gigabytes in 210 files, total running time: 43 hours, 7 minutes, 27 seconds (series 1); in three record boxes
Brooklyn Historical Society collaborated with the Chinatown History Museum (now the Museum of Chinese in America) in order to conduct a series of oral histories with residents of the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. The Cantonese, Mandarin, and English language interviews focused on what was then a new presence of Chinese and Asian immigrants concentrated along Eighth Avenue. Among the topics that are explored in the interviews are tensions between different groups of Chinese immigrants, crime and safety in the neighborhood, Sunset Park's relationship to Manhattan's Chinatown, and how long-term residents of Sunset Park had adjusted to the area's "newcomers."
Brooklyn Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).
Chinatown History Museum.
Chui, Ka-Kam
Lui, Mary
Museum of Chinese in the Americas.
Ruf, Gregory
Administrative History
The New Neighbors: Sunset Park’s Chinese Community oral history project began as a joint effort between Brooklyn Historical Society and the Chinatown History Museum (now the Museum of Chinese in America), with a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and additional funding from the Ford Foundation. Awarded in 1992, the grant endeavored to explore how the new community of Chinese immigrants centered at Brooklyn's Eighth Avenue took root and blossomed during the 1980s. By the early 1990s, the community boasted a population of approximately 60,000 people and was known as New York City’s third Chinatown.
The project’s initial co-directors, Ellen M. Snyder-Grenier of the Brooklyn Historical Society and Mary Ting Yi Lui of the Chinatown History Museum designed the project to create primary documentation of the new ethnic community at a moment when many of its pioneers were still in place. They hoped to answer who these settlers were, and what political and economic forces brought them to Brooklyn. They could find no other materials which directly answered these questions, and believed this study to be the first of its kind in New York City.
By July of 1993, the project’s staff had restructured to include coordinator Gregory Ruf and lead interviewer Ka-Kam Chui. Fabiana Chiu of Brooklyn Historical Society provided additional assistance in interviews.
Cantonese-language interviews were translated and transcribed primarily by Ka-Kam Chui and representatives from the Chinatown History Museum, and exist in handwritten form. English-language interviews were transcribed, and exist in typed form.
For specific information on language please see the scope and content note below for each interview. For the availability of handwritten original-language transcripts for individual interviews, please see transcripts in Box 2.
The oral history project concluded in June of 1996. The New Neighbors: Sunset Park's Chinese Community public exhibitions at both Brooklyn Historical Society and the Chinatown History Museum displayed the oral histories, photographs, and a narrative.
Scope and Contents
Brooklyn Historical Society, in partnership with the Chinatown History Museum, initiated the New Neighbors: Sunset Park’s Chinese Community Oral History project in 1993. Using funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Ford Foundation, twenty-nine interviews were conducted documenting the experiences of both Chinese and non-Chinese community members whose homes clustered around Eighth Avenue in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. Chinese and non-Chinese members of the community were interviewed. While the ethnically-Chinese narrators were chosen to represent both early (pre-1985) and late (post-1985) waves of immigration, non-Chinese narrators were chosen to represent the different ethnic communities who shared the neighborhood with -- or had been displaced by -- the new arrivals. This included people of Latino, Norwegian, and Italian heritage.
This collection includes recordings and transcripts of interviews conducted between March of 1993 and June of 1994. Eleven interviews were conducted in English; fifteen were conducted in Cantonese; and three were conducted in Mandarin. Mary Ting Yi Lui and Ka-Kam Chui performed interviews in Cantonese and English; Gregory Ruf conducted interviews in Mandarin and English. Fabiana Chiu aided on one interview which was conducted with assistance in Spanish. The oral histories often contain descriptions of immigration, living arrangements, neighborhood ethnicities, discrimination, employment, community development, political leadership, petty and organized crime, and adjustment to American life. Also included is a small sampling of newspaper clippings, brochures, and administrative documentation of the project’s development, management, and exhibition.
Arrangement note
The collection contains the digitized content of twenty-nine interviews, digitized and print transcripts in English, Cantonese, and Mandarin (with English translations where applicable), and printed administrative documentation of the project’s development, management, and exhibition. The collection is arranged thematically into 3 series: 1) Oral histories; 2) Oral History Transcripts; 3) Administrative Materials. Interview recordings were originally made on compact cassette tapes and are housed separately.
Series 1: Oral Histories makes up the bulk of the collection. There is audio for each of the twenty-nine interviews, all conducted for the original scope of the project. A complete listing of each interview with a biographical note, scope and content note, and controlled access headings follows. Interviews are also described in the Past Perfect archives catalog, including the audio and transcription where available. Digitized oral histories in Series 1 are in alphabetical order by narrator name.
Series 2: Oral History Transcripts contains handwritten and typed transcripts for each of the twenty-nine interviews, including those in Mandarin and Cantonese along with an English-language translation for most. For a complete listing of translations, participants, and dates of the interview, please see the Interview Lists folder in box 2. Abstracts of the interviews are also included in this series. Folders are organized alphabetically by narrator name. Each folder contains all available transcripts for that interview. When available, digitized transcripts are attached to relevant records in Past Perfect's archives catalog. Contents of box 2 were inventoried and remain unprocessed.
Series 3: Administrative Materials includes all retained materials that went into the funding and implementation for Brooklyn Historical Society and Chinatown History Museum project and exhibition. Materials are arranged as they were found; with separate files pertaining to grant funding, project planning, research, hiring, printed ephemera related to Sunset Park’s Chinese community, and choice of narrators. This series has not been inventoried or processed.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers with varied restrictions according to narrator agreement. Oral histories can be accessed onsite at Brooklyn Historical Society’s Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal. Administrative materials are open to researchers upon request and are accessible onsite at the Othmer Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Materials contained in this collection were generated through the efforts of Brooklyn Historical Society and the Chinatown History Museum.
Related Archival Materials note
In addition to this collection, Brooklyn Historical Society has other oral history collections related to residents of Sunset Park:
• Puerto Rican Oral History Project records, 1960-1984 (1976.001)
• AIDS/Brooklyn Oral History Project collection, 1988-1993 (1993.001)
For more information on these collections, please visit our online finding aid portal.
Oral history collections related to the Chinese American community located at the Museum of Chinese in America include:
• Archeology of Change: Mapping Tales of Gentrification in New York City’s Chinatown
• Chino-Latino Oral Histories collection, 1997-1998, 2003 (2015.007)
• Gotta Sing, Gotta Dance
• Many Voices, One Humanity
• 9/11 Chinatown Documentation Project
Existence and Location of Copies note
This oral history collection is duplicated and stored on-site at MOCA's Collections & Research Center.
Oral History note
Oral history interviews are intimate conversations between two people, both of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with the Brooklyn Historical Society archives and with researchers. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared. Researchers will understand that:
1. The Brooklyn Historical Society abides by the General Principles and Best Practices for Oral History as agreed upon by the Oral History Association (2009) and expects that use of this material will be done with respect for these professional ethics.
2. Every oral history relies on the memories, views and opinions of the narrator. Because of the personal nature of oral history, listeners may find some viewpoints or language of the recorded participants to be objectionable. In keeping with its mission of preservation and unfettered access wherever possible, BHS presents these views as recorded.
3. Transcripts created prior to 2008 serve as a guide to the interview and are not considered verbatim. The audio recording should be considered the primary source for each interview. It may contain natural false starts, verbal stumbles, misspeaks, and repetitions that are common in conversation, and other passages and phrases omitted from the transcript. This decision was made because BHS gives primacy to the audible voice and also because some researchers do find useful information in these verbal patterns.
4. Unless these verbal patterns are germane to your scholarly work, when quoting from this material researchers are encouraged to correct the grammar and make other modifications maintaining the flavor of the narrator’s speech while editing the material for the standards of print.
Community Board No. 4 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Mak, Paul; Administrative records; American Dream; Asian Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; China; China |x History |y 20th century; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans; Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Communism |z China; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Cultural assimilation; Education; English as a second language; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic relations; Exhibition records; Factories |z New York (State) |z New York; Guangzhou (China); Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hong Kong (China); Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Interviews (sound recordings); Multiculturalism; Oral histories (document genres); Queens (New York, N.Y.); Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Real estate business |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); Transcripts; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Working class |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Series 1: Oral histories, Bulk, 1993; 1993 - 1994
- Anonymous, 1993 June 29; 1994.007.01
  Biographical/Historical note
  Born in 1964 to a land-owning family of the educated elite, the narrator's family fortune was reversed during the Chinese Cultural Revolution. At twenty-two, she immigrated to America to attend Clarion University in Pennsylvania. After graduation she moved to New York City and found a job as a librarian in Brooklyn. She later married a Chinese man and helped her parents and sister immigrate to New York City from Toronto, Canada. At the time of the interview, the narrator felt stuck between two cultures; both of which she loved.
  Scope and Contents
  In this interview, the narrator discusses Chinese assimilation to American culture by contrasting her own experiences with those of her younger sister and of her parents. She notes class and lifestyle differences among the different Chinese immigrants of New York City and delineates them by their home provinces, their education levels, their native language, and "old" versus "new" immigrants, while also considering "ABCs" or American-Born Chinese. She discusses ethnic tensions between Chinese American and Hispanic American neighbors in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. The narrator also states that she feels she has become culturally American. Interview conducted by Gregory Ruf.
  Conditions Governing Access and Use
  Access is available onsite at Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and the Oral History Portal. Use of oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires permission from BHS by contacting library@brooklynhistory.org.
  Beijing (China); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; China |x History |x Cultural Revolution, 1966-1976; China |x History |x Tiananmen Square Incident, 1989; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Cultural assimilation; Ethnic relations; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hong Kong (China) |x Politics and government |y 1997-; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Queens County (N.Y.); Social classes; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Anonymous, 1993 July 1; 1994.007.02
  The narrator was born circa 1950 in Taishan, Mainland China. After a brief stay in Hong Kong, her family settled in Saigon, Vietnam, where she lived for thirty years. As an adult, she worked, married, and had five children. The family lived comfortably until the Vietcong conquered South Vietnam and took possession of her family's considerable financial portfolio. Forced to flee, the narrator and her children were granted refugee status in America and settled in Brooklyn. She started numerous entrepreneurial pursuits, including a real estate business. At the time of the 1993 interview, the narrator lived in Brooklyn with her husband and four adult children.
  In this interview, the narrator relates her life story with a backdrop of generations of her family's history. She describes Vietnam; living in Saigon, the Vietcong takeover, her family's process of fleeing, and immigrating to America as a refugee. The narrator discusses her entrepreneurial pursuits by evaluating each business that she started along with each demise. She looks at the real estate business in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn; providing general rent information and identifying the future prospects for the area and its Chinese American residents. Interview in Mandarin conducted by Gregory Ruf.
  mat tran dan toc giai phong mien nam viet nam.; Asian Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; China; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Communism |z Vietnam; Festivals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ho Chi Minh City (Vietnam); Hong Kong (China); Multiculturalism; Real estate business |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Refugees; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Vietnam War, 1961-1975
- Anonymous, 1993 July 1; 1994.007.03
  In her forties when the interview occurred in 1993, the narrator was born in Mainland China and moved with her family to Kowloon, Hong Kong when she was a young girl. The daughter of school teachers from China's educated class, she was taught in private schools, nurtured a love of painting, and studied English in college. In the 1960s, she moved with her husband to New York City, and ultimately settled in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. A mother of four, the narrator also worked outside the home; as a typist, then a bridal gown seamstress, and eventually the owner of a small art gallery.
  In this interview, the narrator provides an overview of her life; both before and after immigrating to New York City from Hong Kong. She discusses her childhood and private schooling in Kowloon, her decision to move to America with her husband and her trip to New York City in the 1960s. The narrator recounts the evolution of her career; from typist, to bridal gown seamstress, to art gallery owner. She offers her thoughts on parenting and practical home economics and provides an overview of the financial situation faced by Chinese immigrants and small business owners. Interview in Mandarin conducted by Gregory Ruf.
  Art |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Artists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |x Education; Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Hong Kong (China) |x Politics and government |y 1997-; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Kowloon (China); Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Castaldo, Louis, 1994 May 17; 1994.007.04
  The son of an Italian father and an Italian-American mother, Louis Castaldo (nickname Lou) was thirty-nine years old in 1994. Castaldo grew up in Brooklyn. During his childhood, he lived in the Bensonhurst neighborhood of Brooklyn and attended public schools within the area. In the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn, Castaldo's father, Vinnie, bought and ran Vinnie's Pizzeria as a family business from 1970 onward. Castaldo worked alongside his father at the pizzeria from his early teen years to the time of the interview in 1994.
  In this interview, Lou Castaldo discusses his father's business; Vinnie's Pizzeria was established during the early 1970s in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. He recounts his father's coming to America and life before starting the business. Castaldo describes the various ethnic cultures and neighborhoods he observed while growing up in Brooklyn; including significant events, activities, hobbies, family life and traditions. Castaldo recalls a significant period of change in Sunset Park, beginning in 1979; from a European American neighborhood comprised of Germans, Greeks, Irish, Italians, and Norwegians to an Asian American neighborhood, largely of Chinese heritage. He evaluates other influences that factored into the changing neighborhood; escalating crime rates and drug use, business closures, new Chinese American ownership of businesses and housing, cultural differences and language barriers, and national politics supporting or allowing illegal aliens to enter and live in the United States. He surveys the Sunset Park community's actions to create a more global and shared sense of community—a melting pot of cultures. Interview conducted by Gregory Ruf.
  Castaldo, Louis; Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Chinese Americans; Ethnic identity; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Italian Americans |x Social life and customs; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Chan, Guo Wa, 1993 June 29; 1994.007.05
  Born in Guangzhou, China in 1955, Guo Wa "Grace" Chan immigrated to New York City in 1981 to join her husband after he had come to America almost a decade earlier. In 1985 Chan opened Prosperity Video, the first Chinese-language movie rental store in the Chinatown area within the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn, because she realized she could care for her new baby while running the shop. At the time of the 1993 interview, Chan was the busy mother of four children. While working three hundred sixty-four days a year at the shop, in the evenings she was an active parent with a particular interest in her children's progress at school. Chan looked forward to one day taking her children on vacation to Florida.
  In this interview, Guo Wa "Grace" Chan discusses her immigration and life in New York City. She focuses on her experiences as a businesswoman, detailing the launch of her video rental store. She mentions her husband's ventures in the restaurant industry. Chan describes the entrepreneurial competition in Brooklyn's Chinatown and real estate prices, commercial as well as residential. An educationally-focused mother, Chan evaluates the educational decisions she has made and the quality of local public and private schools. Interview in Cantonese conducted by Mary Lui.
  Chan, Guo Wa; Chinatown Planning Council (New York, N.Y.).; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family-owned business enterprises |x Chinese Americans; Guangzhou (China); Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Chan, Kwok-Wai, 1993 April 17; 1994.007.06
  Kwok-Wai "David" Chan was born in Mainland China in 1955. In 1975 Chan emigrated with his family from Hong Kong to New York City and immediately settled in Brooklyn. He was nineteen at the time. Chan received a bachelor's degree in Accounting from State University of New York Buffalo. After college, Chan eventually found his vocation as an entrepreneur. At the time of the 1993 interview, Chan was the owner of a pharmacy in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn that catered to local Chinese-American immigrants. Chan married and was a father to two daughters. In 1993, the family lived in a newly-purchased home in Staten Island.
  In this interview Kwok-Wai "David" Chan relates his experience as a Chinese immigrant to New York City. He describes his reasons for emigrating, the family's arrival to Brooklyn, and hardships faced soon after. He discusses his education and the value his family places in higher education -- something he calls a Chinese value. Chan details his career as an entrepreneur; including failures, challenges, and accomplishments. Throughout the interview, Chan discusses the community changes he's watched over the last few decades. Interview conducted by Mary Lui.